Learning-SICP 学习小组
倾情制作
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
翻译&&时间轴
邓雄飞
刘殊君
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
显示控制求值器
PROFESSOR: Well, I hope you appreciate that we have
教授：我想大家已经意识到
we have inducted you into some real magic,
我们介绍了一些真正的魔法
the magic of building languages
创造新语言的魔法
really building new languages.
用来创造全新的语言
What have we looked at?
我们学了些什么？
We've looked at an Escher picture language.
我们学习了一门用来操作图片的Escher的语言
OK? this language invented by Peter Henderson.
这门语言由Peter Henderson发明
We looked at digital logic language.
我们还学习了数字逻辑语言
Let's see.We've looked at the query language.
以及 我们还学习了查询语言
And the thing you should realize is,
然而你需要明白的是
even though these were toy examples,
尽管它们都是“玩具级”的语言示例
they really are the kernels of really useful things.
但也确实是实用工具的核心
So, for instance,
比如说
the Escher picture language
Escher图片语言
was taken byHenry Wu, who's a student at MIT,
就被MIT的学生Henry Wu拿去
and developed into a real
开发成了一门用于
language for laying out PC boards,
为电路板布局的语言
based just on extending those structures.
它就是在这些结构上扩展而来
And the digital logic language,
至于数字逻辑语言
Gerry mentioned when he showed it to you,
Gerry教授在上课的时候也提到过
was really extended to be used as the basis for a simulator
它被扩展为了一个仿真器的基础
that was used to design a real computer.
用来设计真实的计算机
And the query language,
至于查询语言
of course, is kind of the germ of prolog.
当然就是Prolog语言的一种核心
So we built all of these languages,
我们构造的这些语言
they're all based on LISP.
全都是用Lisp编写
A lot of people ask
很多人问
what particular problems is LISP good for solving for?
Lisp适合用来解决哪一类问题？
The answer is LISP is not...
答案就是
LISP is not good for solving any particular problems.
Lisp不适合解决任何一类问题
What LISP is good for
Lisp擅长的是
is constructing within it the right language
用它来构造一门合适的语言
to solve the problems you want to solve,
来解决你的问题
and that's how you should think about it.
你应该像这样看待Lisp
So all of these languages were based on LISP.
那么既然这些语言都基于Lisp
Now, what's LISP based on?
那Lisp又基于什么？
Where's that come from?
它又从何而来？
Well, we looked at that too.
这个我们也学过
We looked at the meta-circular evaluator
我们学过元循环求值器
the meta-circular evaluator and sort of said
学习了元循环求值器后 我们说
well, LISP is based on LISP.
Lisp就是基于Lisp的
And when we start looking at that,
而当我们研究它的时候
we've got to do some real magic, right?
我们必须得施展一些真正的魔法 对吧？
So what does that mean, right?
这又是什么意思呢？
Y operators, and fixed points,
Y算子、不动点
and the idea that what this means is
以及这样的一个观念--
that LISP is somehow the fixed-point equation for the
Lisp实际上是一个方程的不动点
for this funny set of things which are defined in terms of themselves.
一个通过自身来定义的有趣方程
Now, it's real magic.
这确实是神奇的魔法
Well, today, for a final piece of magic,
那么今天 作为魔法的最后一步
we're going to make all the magic go away.
我们要把它们通通消除掉
We already know how to do that.
我们已经知道怎么做了
The idea is, we're going to take
核心要思想是
the register machine architecture
将Lisp语言
and show how to implement LISP on terms of that.
实现在使用寄存器架构的机器上
And, remember, the idea of the register machine
回想一下 寄存器机器的关键之处在于
is that there's a fixed and finite part of the machine.
机器的一部分是确定且有穷的
There's a finite-state controller,
它有一个有穷状态控制器
which dose particular thing
它用特定的硬件
with a particular amount of hardware.
去完成特定的事情
There are particular data paths,
其中还有一些运算所需的
the operation the machine does
特殊数据通路
And then, in order to implement recursion
然后 为了实现递归
and sustain the illusion of infinity,
并且维持无穷的假象
there's some large amount of memory, which is the stack.
还使用了一种称作“栈”的大内存
So, if we implement LISP
所以如果我们在
in terms of a register machine,
寄存器机器上实现了Lisp
then everything ought to become,
那么这个时候
at this point,completely concrete.
所有的东西都会完全具体化
All the magic should go away.
所有的魔法都会消除
And, by the end of this talk,
这堂课结束时
I want you get the feeling
我想让你感觉到
that, as opposed to this very mysterious meta-circular evaluator
相对于神秘的元循环求值器
that a LISP evaluator really is something that's concrete enough
Lisp求值器是非常具体的东西
that you can hold in the palm of your hand.
你甚至可以把它放在手心中
You should be able to imagine holding
你可以想象一下
holding a LISP interpreter there.
手里拿着一个Lisp解释器的情景
All right, how are we going to do this?
好 那我们怎么做呢？
We already have all the ingredients.
所有的原料都已经齐全
See, what you learned last time from Gerry
上节课Gerry教了你们
is how to take any particular couple of LISP procedures.
对一个任意的Lisp过程
and hand-translate them
如何手动地把它们
into something that runs on a register machine.
翻译成在寄存器机器上运行的代码
So, to implement all of LISP on a register machine,
那么 要在寄存器机器上实现Lisp本身
all we have to do
我们只需要
is take the particular procedures
把最关键的过程
that are the meta-circular evaluator
也就是元循环求值器
and hand-translate them for a register machine.
手工翻译成寄存器机器的代码
And that does all of LISP
这就实现了整个Lisp
Right? So, in principle,
因此 我们已经知道了
we already know how to do this.
实现的原理
And, indeed, it's going to be no
而且实际上
no different, in kind,
这跟翻译
from in say recursive factorial
递归版的阶乘或斐波那契数列
or recursive Fibonacci.
没什么区别
It's just bigger and there's more of it.
只是它规模更大 代码更多
So it'd just be more details,
只是包含了更多细节
but nothing really conceptually new.
但是没有任何新的概念
And also, when we've done that,
当我们完成这个以后
and the thing is completely explicit,
所有的东西都变得明确了
and we see how to implement LISP
当我们看到如何用一系列的
in terms of the actual sequential register operations,
寄存器操作来实现Lisp之后
that's going to be our final
它就成为了我们整个课程中
most explicit model of LISP in this course.
最明确的Lisp模型
And, remember, that's a progression through this course.
回忆一下 这个过程贯穿了整个课程
We started out with substitution,
我们先从代换模型开始
which is sort of like algebra.
它和代数有点相似
And then we went to the environment model,
然后学习了环境模型
which talked about the actual frames
它引入了“框架”的概念
and how they got linked together.
以及框架之间的关联
And then we made that more concrete
然后我们在元循环求值器中
in the meta-circular evaluator.
把它变得更具体了
There are things
但是有的事情
the meta-circular evaluator doesn't tell us.
元循环求值器没有告诉我们
You should realize that.
你应该认识到这点
For instance, it left unanswered the question
比如说 我们还不知道
of how a procedure, like recursive factorial here,
像这里的递归阶乘过程
somehow takes space that grows.
为何不断地申请新的空间
On the other hand,
另一方面
a procedure which also looks syntactically recursive,
一个语法上看起来像是递归的过程
called fact-iter, somehow doesn't take space.
比如FACT-ITER 并不占用栈空间
We justify that it doesn't need to take space
我们通过代换模型来证明
by showing the substitution model.
它不占用空间
But we didn't really say
但我们并没有说清楚
how it happens that the machine manages to do that,
机器是如何做到这一点的
that that has to do with the details
这涉及到一些细节
of how arguments are passed to procedures
比如参数是如何传递给过程的
And that's the thing we didn't see
这是我们在元循环求值器中
in the meta-circular evaluator
没有看到的
precisely because the way arguments
完全是因为在所实现的Lisp中
got passed to procedures in this LISP
把参数传递给过程的方式
depended on
取决于
the way arguments got passed to procedures in this LISP.
外部Lisp的传参方式
But, now, that's going to become extremely explicit.
但现在 这一点将变得非常明确
OK.
好
Well, before going on to the evaluator,
在开始研究求值器之前
let me just give you a sense of
我先让你们感受一下
what a whole LISP system looks like
一个完整Lisp系统是怎么样的
so you can see the parts we're going to talk about
这样你就可以知道 我们要讨论哪部分
and the parts we're not going to talk about.
不讨论哪些部分
Let's see, over here is a happy LISP user,
首先 这里有一个快乐的Lisp用户
and the LISP user is talking to something called the reader.
他正在和一个叫做读取器的东西交流
The reader's job in life
读取器的工作是
is to take characters from the user
读取用户输入的字符串
and turn them into data structures
把它们转化成一种称作
in something called a list structure memory.
表结构内存的数据结构
All right, so the reader is going to take
读取器会读取--
symbols, parentheses,
你敲出来的符号、括号
and A's and B's, and 1s and 3s that you type in,
A和B、1和3这些东西
and turn these into actual list structure:
并把它们变成表结构
pairs, and pointers, and things.
变成序对、指针等等
And so, by the time evaluator is going,
所以当求值器运行的时候
there are no characters in the world.
环境里已经不存在原始字符了
And, of course, in more modern Lisp systems, there's
当然 在更现代的Lisp系统中
there's sort a big morass here
可能还有一大团东西
that might sit between the user and the reader:
存在于在读取器和用户之间
you know, Windows systems, in top levels,
最顶层首先是视窗系统
and mice, and all kinds of things.
以及鼠标之类的东西
But conceptually, characters are coming in.
但从概念上来说 都是在输入字符
All right, the reader transforms these into pointers
总之 读取器把它们都变成指针
pointers to stuff in this memory,
指向内存中的对象
and that's what the evaluator sees
这是求值器的所能看到的东西
OK?
明白吗？
The evaluator has a bunch of helpers.
求值器有一些辅助函数
It has all possible primitive operators you might want.
包括你需要的所有基本运算
So there's a completely separate box,
也就是说这里另有一盒子东西
a floating point unit,
比如浮点单元
or all sorts of things, which do the primitive operators.
或者其它类似的东西来执行这些运算
there's and, if you want more special primitives,
如果你需要支持更多的基本运算
you build more primitive operators,
你就实现更多的运算符执行器
but they're separate from the evaluator.
但它们和求值器都是分离的
The evaluator finally gets an answer
求值器最终算出结果
and communicates that to the printer.
并且把它们告诉打印程序
And now, the printer's job in life
现在 打印程序的任务就是
is this list structure coming from the evaluator,
从求值器取得这个表结构
and turn it back into characters,
再把它们变回字符
and communicate them to the user through
然后通过某种界面
whatever interface there is.
展示给用户
OK. Well, today, what we're going to talk about is this evaluator.
那么 今天我们要讨论的是这个求值器
The primitive operators have nothing particular to do with LISP,
基本运算和Lisp没有什么特别的关系
they're however you like to implement primitive operations.
它们只取决于你怎么实现基本运算
The reader and printer are actually complicated,
读取器和打印程序实际上很复杂
but we're not going to talk about them.
但是我们不去讨论它们
They sort of have to do with details of how you might build
从字符构建表的过程中
build up list structure from characters.
它们需要处理很多细节
So that is a long story,
说来话长
but we're not going to talk about it,
我们就不讨论它了
the list structure memory,
关于表结构内存
we'll talk about next time.
我们下次再来讨论
So, pretty much, except for the details of reading and printing,
那么去除了读取和打印的细节
the only mystery that's going to be left
关于这个求值器
after you see the evaluator
所剩下的唯一谜团
is how you build list structure on conventional memories.
几乎就只有怎么在传统内存上构建表结构了
But we'll worry about that next time too.
不过我们把那也放到下次来讨论
OK.
好
Well, let's start talking about the evaluator.
那么 我们先来看看这个求值器
The one that we're going to show you,
我将要展示的这个求值器
of course, is not, I think, nothing special about it.
我想 它并没有什么特别的
It's just a particular register machine that runs LISP.
它只是一台专门运行Lisp的寄存器机器
And it has seven registers,
它有七个寄存器
and here are the seven registers.
这是它的七个寄存器
There's a register, called EXP
这个寄存器叫EXP
and its job is to hold
它的任务是存放
the expression to be evaluated.
将要被求值的表达式
And by that, I mean
具体来说
it's going to hold a pointer
它存放的是一个指针
to someplace in list structure memory
指针指向存放着求值的表达式
the expression to be evaluated.
的一处表结构内存
There's a register, called ENV,
还有一个叫做ENV的寄存器
which holds the environment
它存放着环境
in which this expression is to be evaluated.
也就是表达式的求值环境
And, again, I made a pointer.
同样的 这也是一个指针
The environment is some data structure.
环境是一种数据结构
There's a register, called FUN, which will
这个叫做FUN的寄存器--
which will hold the procedure to be applied
当你在应用一个过程时
when you go to apply a procedure.
它会存放这个过程
A register, called ARGL,
还有寄存器ARGL
which holds the list of evaluated arguments.
它存放的是已求值的参数
What you can start seeing here is
从这里开始你能看到
the basic structure of the evaluator.
求值器的基本构造
Remember how evaluators work.
回忆一下它是怎么工作的
There's a piece that takes expressions and environments,
对这一块输入表达式和环境
and there's a piece that takes functions
而这一块接收函数
or procedures and arguments.
或者说 过程以及参数
And going back and forth around here is the eval/apply loop.
EVAL-APPLY循环使用这些寄存器工作
So those are the basic pieces of the eval and apply.
所以这些是EVAL-APPLY的基本组成部分
Then there's some other things,
还有一些别的东西
there's continue.
比如CONTINUE寄存器
You just saw before how the continue register is used to
你之前已经见过CONTINUE寄存器
implement recursion and stack discipline.
是如何实现递归以及栈操作的
There's a register that's going to hold the
还有个寄存器用来存放
result of some evaluation.
某个求值的结果
And then, besides that,
然后 除了这些以外
there's one temporary register,
还有一个临时寄存器
called UNEV,
它就是UNEV
which typically, in the evaluator,
一般来讲 在求值器中
is going to be used to hold temporary pieces of the
它是用来存放正在求值的表达式
expression you're working on,
的临时部分
which you haven't gotten around to evaluate yet
就是那些尚未求值的部分
Right? So there's my machine: a seven-register machine.
那么 这就是我的七寄存器机器
And, of course, you might want to make a machine with
当然 你可能想造一台
a lot more registers to get better performance,
有更多寄存器的机器 来取得更好性能
but this is just a tiny, minimal one.
但我们这个只是一台小型机器
Well, how about the data paths?
那么数据通路呢？
This machine has a lot of special operations for LISP.
这台机器有很多专为Lisp设计的运算
So, here are some typical data paths.
这里有几条典型的数据通路
A typical one might be,
其中一条可能是
oh, assign to the VAL register
将EXP寄存器的值
the contents of the EXP register.
赋给VAL寄存器
That's in terms of those diagrams you saw,
用我们之前的数据通路图来说
that's a little button on some arrow.
就是一条箭头上的小按钮
Here's a more complicated one.
这还有一个更复杂的
It says branch,
它判断
if the thing in the expression register is a conditional
如果EXP寄存器的内容是COND语句
to some label here, called the ev-conditional.
那么这里就会跳转到EV-COND标号处
And you can imagine this implemented in a lot of different ways.
你可以想象出很多种实现它的方法
You might imagine this conditional test
你可以把这个判断看作是
as a special purpose sub-routine,
一个特殊意图的子过程
and conditional might be represented as some data abstraction
而条件被表示成某种数据抽象
that you don't care about at this level of detail.
你在这个层面上不用考虑它
So that might be done as a sub-routine.
那么它可以用子过程实现
This might be a machine with hardware-types,
如果机器通过硬件来判断表达式类型
and conditional might be testing some bits for a particular code.
那么某些特定比特就代表了COND语句
There are all sorts of ways that's
有很多种实现办法
beneath the level of abstraction we're looking at.
它们都低于我们关注的这一层抽象
Another kind of operation,
然后还有另一种操作
and there are a lot of different operations
以及其它很多操作
assigned to EXP, the first clause of what's in EXP.
把EXP的第一个子句赋值给EXP
This might be part of processing a conditional.
这可能是处理COND语句的一部分
And, again, first clause is some selector
同样 FIRST-SELECTOR这个选择子
whose details we don't care about.
我们也不需要关心它的细节
And you can, again, imagine that as a sub-routine
同样可以把那也看成一个子过程
which'll do some list operations,
用来进行一些表操作
or you can imagine that as
或者你也可以想象成
something that's built directly into hardware.
一个直接构建在硬件中的东西
The reason I keep saying you can imagine it
我之所以强调
built directly into hardware
你可以把它想象成硬件直接实现
is even though there are a lot of operations,
是因为尽管有很多的运算
there are still a fixed number of them.
但也它们的数量也是固定的
I forget how many, maybe 150.
我记不清有多少 大概有150个
So, it's plausible to think of building these directly into hardware.
所以假设用硬件实现它们是合理的
Here's a more complicated one.
而这一条更加复杂
You can see this has to do with
你会发现 这条涉及到
looking up the values of variables.
查找变量的值
It says assign to the VAL register
它会查找某条表达式中
the result of looking up the variable value
某个变量的值
of some particular expression,
并赋值给VAL寄存器
which, in this case, is supposed to be
在本例中 也就是
a variable in some environment.
在某个环境中查找变量
And this'll be some operation
然后这个操作
that search through the environment structure,
会搜索整个环境结构
however it is represented,
无论环境是如何表示的
and goes and looks up that variable.
并查找该变量
And, again, that's below the level of detail
同样 它也不在我们思考的
that we're thinking about.
的抽象层面上
This is... this has to do with the details of
它需要处理的细节是
the data structures for representing environments.
用来表示环境的数据结构
But, anyway, there is this
但是不管怎么说
there is this fixed and finite number
这就是这台寄存器机器的
of operations in the register machine.
有穷数量的固定操作
Well, what's its overall structure?
那么 它的整体结构是什么样子的？
Those are some typical operations.
这有几个典型的运算
Remember what we have to do,
想一想 我们要做什么
we have to take the meta-circular evaluator--
我们需要把元循环求值器
and here's a piece of the meta-circular evaluator.
这就是元循环求值器的一部分
This is the one using abstract syntax that's in the book.
这是书中使用抽象代码的版本
It's a little bit different from the one that Gerry shows you.
它和Gerry教授给你们展示的有些不同
And the main thing
关于求值器
to remember about the evaluator is that
主要需要记住的是
it's doing some sort of case analysis on the kinds of expressions:
它是某种针对表达式类型的分情况分析
so if it's either self-evaluated, or quoted,
看它是否为自求值的 或被引用的
or whatever else.
或是别的什么
And then, in the general case where
而在大部分情况下
the expression it's looking at is an application,
它处理的是一个过程应用
there's some tricky recursions going on.
那么里面有一些技巧性的递归过程
First of all, eval has to call itself
首先 EVAL要调用它自己
both to evaluate the operator
来求值运算符以及
and to evaluate all the operands.
所有的运算对象
So there's this sort of red recursion
因此这些标红线的地方
of values walking down the tree
就是某种在语法树上的递归
that's sort of the easy recursion.
这是很简单的递归
That's just eval walking down this tree of expressions.
只是EVAL在递归地遍历语法树
Then, in the evaluator,
然后在求值器中
there's a hard recursion.
有一个复杂的递归
There's the red to green.
由绿线到红线的递归
Eval calls apply.
由EVAL调用APPLY
That's the case where evaluating a procedure argument
也就是把过程调用
reduces to applying the procedure
归约为了 将过程应用在
to the list of arguments.
实参表上
And then, apply comes over here.
然后请看APPLY
Apply takes a procedure and arguments
APPLY需要过程PROC和参数ARGS
and, in the general case
一般情况下
where there's a compound procedure,
PROC都是一个复合过程
apply goes around and
随着APPLY不断被调用
green calls red.
绿线处会调用红线处
Eval-- Apply comes around and calls eval again.
APPLY被调用并再次调用EVAL
Eval's the body of the procedure
EVAL会求值过程体
in the result of extending the environment
基于一个扩展了的环境
with the parameters of the procedure
这个环境通过将过程的形式参数
by binding the arguments.
与实际参数绑定起来而得
Except in the primitive case,
而对于最基本的情况
where it just calls something else primitive-apply
它会调用PRIMITIVE-APPLY过程
which is not really the business of the evaluator.
而那又不是求值器的工作了
So this sort of red to green,
那么像这样从红到绿
to red to green,
又到红又到绿
Right? That's the that's the eval/apply loop,
这就是EVAL-APPLY循环
and that's the thing that we're going to want to see
这就是我们在求值器中
in the evaluator.
想要看到的东西
Well, it won't surprise you at all that
这样 你不会惊异于
the two big pieces of this evaluator
这个求值器的两大部分
are correspond to eval and apply.
对应于EVAL-APPLY
There's a piece called eval-dispatch,
一个部分叫EVAL-DISPATCH
and a piece called apply-dispatch.
另一部分叫做APPLY-DISPATCH
And, before we get into the details of the code,
在我们关注代码细节之前
the way to understand this is to think,
理解它们的方法就是
again, in terms of these pieces of evaluator
假设这些求值器的各个部分
having contracts with the rest of the world.
和这个世界中其它的部分有一些约定
What do they do from the outside
在进入这些肮脏的细节前
before getting into the grungy details?
它们在外部做了什么？
Well, the contract for eval-dispatch--
针对EVAL-DISPATCH的约定
remember, it corresponds to eval.
还记得吗 它对应的是EVAL
It's got to evaluate an expression in an environment.
它要在环境中求值一个表达式
So, in particular, what this one is going to do,
那么 这部分要做的就是
eval-dispatch will assume that, when you call it,
EVAL-DISPATCH会假设当你调用它的时候
that the expression you want to evaluate
你想要求值的表达式
is in the EXP register.
就存放在EXP寄存器中
The environment in which you want the evaluation
而求值所基于的环境
to take place is in the ENV register.
则存放在ENV环境中
And continue tells you
而CONTINUE寄存器用来指示
the place where the machine should go next
当求值完成后
when the evaluation is done.
机器需要去向何方
Eval-dispatch's contract is that
EVAL-DISPATCH的约定实际上就是
it'll actually perform that evaluation,
它会执行实际的求值
and, at the end of which,
并且在求值结束后
it'll end up at the place specified by continue.
它会转到由CONTINUE寄存器指定的位置
The result of the evaluation will be in the VAL register.
求值的结果会存放在VAL寄存器中
And it just warns you,
需要提醒的是
it makes no promises about
它对其余的寄存器
what happens to rest the registers.
不做任何承诺
All other registers might be destroyed.
其它所有的寄存器都可能被修改
So, there's one piece, OK?
那么这是一部分
Together, the pieces, apply-dispatch
这些部分一块构成了APPLY-DISPATCH
that corresponds to apply,
它们对应了APPLY
it's got to apply a procedure to some arguments,
用来把一个过程应用在一些参数上
so it assumes that this register, ARGL,
因此它假设ARGL寄存器
contains a list of the evaluated arguments.
存放着求值后的参数列表
FUN contains the procedure.
FUN寄存器存放着那个过程
Those correspond to the arguments to
它们对应于元循环求值器中的
the apply procedure in the meta-circular evaluator.
参数应用部分
And apply, in this particular evaluator,
在我们的这个求值器中
we're going to use a discipline which says
我们APPLY时采用的约定是
the place that apply
当APPLY完成后--
the place the machine should go to next
机器应该跳转到
when apply is done, is at the moment
的下一个地方应该是
apply-dispatch is called at the top of the stack
APPLY-DISPATCH被调用时的栈顶元素
that's just discipline for the way this particular machine's organized.
这只是针对这台机器的约定
And now apply's contract is given all that.
现在已经给出了APPLY的所有约定
It'll perform the application.
它会去执行应用
The result of that application will end up in VAL.
这个应用的结果将会保存在VAL寄存器中
The stack will be popped.
栈会被弹出
And, again,
同样的
the contents of all the other registers may be destroyed.
其它所有寄存器的内容都可能被修改
All right? So that's the basic organization of this machine.
那么 这就是这台机器的基本结构
Let's break for a little bit and see if there are any questions
我们先课间休息一下
and then we'll do a real example.
然后再来研究一个真实的例子
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Sussman Jay Sussman
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
显式控制求值器
Well, let's take the register machine now,
现在 我们来研究一下这台寄存器机器
and actually step through,
我们一步一步地跟进
and really, in real detail,
具体到每一处细节
so you see completely concrete
这样你就能完全具体地看到
how some expressions are evaluated,
表达式是如何求值的
Alright? So, let's start with a very simple expression.
那么我们从一个非常简单的表达式开始
Let's evaluate the expression 1.
我们要求值的表达式只有一个1
And we need an environment,
我们需要一个环境
so let's imagine that somewhere there's an environment
因此我们假设某处有一个环境
we'll call it E0.
我们把它记作E0
And just, since we'll use these later,
由于我们之后也要用到它
we obviously don't really need anything
而且显然不需要任何东西
to evaluate 1.
就可以求值1
But, just for reference later,
但是为了方便以后引用
let's assume that E0 has in it
我们假设环境E0中有
an X that's bound to 3
X=3
and a Y that's bound to 4,
Y=4
OK?
好吗？
And now what we're going to do
现在 我们要做的就是
is we're going to evaluate 1 in this environment
在这个环境中求值表达式1
and so the ENV register has a pointer
这样 ENV寄存器就存放了一个指针
to this environment, E0, all right?
指向这个环境E0
Right? So let's watch that thing go.
那么我们来看它是怎么进行的
What I'm going to do is step through the code.
我要步步跟进代码
And, let's see, I'll be the controller.
这样的话 我会充当控制器
And now what I need,
现在我需要的是--
since this gets rather complicated,
由于这台机器已经变得相当复杂
is a very little execution unit.
我需要一个小小的执行单元
So here's the execution unit, OK?
那么请上我们的执行单元
OK.
好的
All right, now we're going to start.
好 现在我们要开始了
We're going to start the machine at eval-dispatch。
我们要从EVAL-DISPATCH启动机器
Right? That's the beginning of this.
这是整个过程的开始
Eval-dispatch is going to look at the expression and dispatch,
EVAL-DISPATCH会查看表达式并进行分派
just like eval
就像EVAL
where we look at the very first thing.
先从第一句看起
We branch on whether or not this expression is self-evaluating.
先判断表达式是不是自求值的
Self-evaluating is some abstraction
SELF-EVALUATING?是我们放入机器的
we put into the machine--
一个抽象过程
it's going to be true for numbers--
它对于数字1来说为真
to a place called ev-self-eval,
因此跳转的目的是EV-SELF-EVAL
So me, being the controller,
那么我作为控制器
looks at ev-self-eval,
会去查看EV-SELF-EVAL
so we'll go over to there.
所以我们要跳到那里
Ev-self-eval says fine,
EV-SELF-EAVL的代码是--
assign to val whatever is in the expression unit.
把EXP寄存器的值赋值给VAL寄存器
And I have a bug
我遇到一个BUG
because what I didn't do when I initialized this machine
因为我初始化机器的时候没有做一件事情
is also say what's supposed
也就是指定当它执行完毕后
to happen when it's done,
应该做什么
so I should have started out the machine
所以在启动机器的时候
with done being in the continue register,
应该将CONTINUE寄存器设置为DONE
OK? So we assign to VAL.
所以我们给VAL赋值
And now go to fetch of continue,
然后执行(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
and now change--
并且修改--
OK.
好
OK, let's try something harder.
好 我们来看一个更复杂的
Let's reset the machine here,
我们先重置机器
and we'll put in the expression register, X, OK?
然后把X放入EXP寄存器中
Start again at eval-dispatch.
重新从EVAL-DISPATCH开始
Check, is it self-evaluating?
先检查它是自求值的么？
No.
不是
Is it a variable?
它是变量吗
Yes.
是的
We go off to ev-variable.
我们跳转到EV-VARIABLE
It says assign to VAL,
它说：查找EXP寄存器中变量的值
look up the variable value in the expression register
并把它赋值给VAL寄存器
Go to fetch of continue.
(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
PROFESSOR: Done.
Sussman教授：DONE
PROFESSOR: OK.
Abelson教授：好
Alright, Well, that's the basic idea. Those're
这些都是最基本的理念
That's a simple operation of the machine.
这是这台机器上的简单运算
Now, let's actually do something a little bit more interesting.
现在 我们来做些有意义的事情
Let's look at the expression
我们看这条表达式
the sum of x and y.
(+ X Y)
OK. And now we'll see how you start
现在我们会看到
unrolling these expression trees.
如何展开这些表达式树
Well, start again at eval-dispatch.
我们再次从EVAL-DISPATCH开始
Self-evaluating?
是自求值的吗？
No.
不是
Variable? No.
是变量吗？不是
All the other special forms
它也不是我在这里
which I didn't write down,
没有列出的特殊形式
like quote, and lambda, and set, and whatever,
比如引用、LAMBDA、SET! 等等
it's none of those.
它都不是
It turns out to be an application,
它是一个过程应用
so we go off to ev-application.
所以我们要跳转到EV-APPLICATION
Ev-application, remember what it's going to do overall.
回忆一下EV-APPLICATION要做什么
It is going to evaluate the operator.
它先要求值运算符
It's going to evaluate the arguments,
然后求值运算对象
and then it's going to go apply them.
然后再进行应用
So, before we start,
所以在我们开始之前
since we're being very literal,
由于我们是严格按照代码来执行的
we'd better remember that,
我们最好记住
somewhere in this environment,
在这个环境中的某处
it's linked to another environment
连接到了另一个环境
in which plus
其中符号'+
is bound to the primitive procedure plus
跟基本的加法过程绑定在了一起
before we get an unknown variable in our machine.
这样 求值+时就不会导致“变量未定义”
OK, so we're at ev-application.
现在我们来到了EV-APPLICATION
OK, assign to UNEV the operands
把EXP寄存器对应的运算对象
of what's in the expression register.
赋值给UNEV寄存器
OK. Those are the operands.
这些是运算对象
UNEV's a temporary register
UNEV这个临时寄存器
where we're going to save them.
就是用来暂存它们的
PROFESSOR: I'm assigning.
Sussman教授：我正在赋值
PROFESSOR: Assign to EXP the operator.
Abelson教授：把运算符赋值给EXP寄存器
Now, notice we've destroyed that expression in EXP,
注意 现在我们已经修改了EXP中的表达式
but the piece that we need is now in UNEV.
但是我们需要的部分在UNEV中
Now, we're going to get set up to
现在 我们要准备好
to recursively evaluate the operator.
去递归地求值运算符
Save the continue register on the stack.
把CONTINUE寄存器保存在栈上
Save the environment.
保存ENV
Save UNEV.
保存UNEV
OK, assign to continue a label called eval-args.
把标号EVAL-ARGS赋值给CONTINUE寄存器
Now, what have we done?
我们做了什么
We've set up for a recursive call.
我们为递归调用做了必要的准备
We're about to go to eval-dispatch.
我们要开始执行EVAL-DISPATCH
We've set up for a recursive call to eval-dispatch.
我们为递归调用EVAL-DISPATCH做好了准备
What did we do?
我们做了哪些事情
We took the things we're going to need later,
我们把之后要用到的东西
those operands that were in UNEV;
也就是UNEV中的运算对象
the environment in which we're going to eventually have to,
以及我们最终求值运算对象时
maybe, evaluate those operands;
会用到的环境
the place we eventually want to go to,
以及我们最终想要去的位置
which, in this case, was done;
本例中 也就是DONE
we've saved them on the stack.
我们把它们保存在栈上
The reason we saved them on the stack
我们之所以把它们保存在栈上
is because eval-dispatch makes no promises
是因为EVAL-DISPATCH并不会保证
about what registers it may destroy.
不会去修改这些寄存器
So all that stuff is saved on the stack.
那么所有这些东西都存在了栈上
Now, we've set up eval-dispatch's contract.
现在我们满足了EVAL-DISPATCH的约定
There's a new expression,
这是一条新的表达式
which is the operator plus;
也就是+运算符
a new environment,
以及一个新的环境
although, in this case, it's the same one;
尽管在本例中是同一个环境
and a new place to go to when you're done,
以及在完成后要返回的位置
which is eval-args.
也就是EVAL-ARGS
So that's set up.
这样就满足了
Now, we're going to go off to eval-dispatch.
现在我们来执行EVAL-DISPATCH
Here we are back at eval-dispatch.
我们回到了EVAL-DISPATCH
It's not self-evaluating.
它不是自求值的
Oh, it's a variable,
但它是一个变量
so we'd better go off to ev-variable,
因此我们最好跳转到EV-VARIABLE
Right? Ev-variable is assigned to VAL.
EV-VARIABLE首先要给VAL赋值
Look up the variable value of the expression,
查找表达式中变量的值
OK? So VAL is the primitive procedure plus.
那么VAL寄存器中应该是基本的加法运算
And go to fetch of continue.
然后(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
PROFESSOR: Eval-args.
Sussman教授：它是EVAL-ARGS
PROFESSOR: Right, which is now eval-args not done.
Abelson教授：现在它是EVAL-ARGS而不是DONE了
So we come back here at eval-args,
然后我们来到EVAL-ARGS
and what do we do?
看看它要做什么
We're going to restore the stuff that we saved,
我们要恢复之前保存的东西
so we restore UNEV.
因此调用(RESTORE UNEV)
And notice, there, it wasn't necessary,
注意 这里并不是必要的
although, in general, it would be.
但通常来说都会有这么一步
It might be some arbitrary evaluation that happened.
它可以是任意的求值过程
We restore ENV.
恢复ENV寄存器
OK, we assign to FUN fetch of VAL.
然后把(FETCH VAL)赋值给FUN
OK, now, we're going to go off and start evaluating some arguments.
现在我们要开始求值参数了
Well, first thing we'd better do is save FUN
首先 我们最好把FUN寄存器保存起来
because some arbitrary stuff might happen in that evaluation.
因为求值过程中可能发生任何事情
We initialize the argument list.
我们初始化参数列表
Assign to argl an empty argument list,
给ARGL赋值一个空的参数列表
and go to eval-arg-loop,
然后跳转到EVAL-ARG-LOOP
At eval-arg-loop,
在EVAL-ARG-LOOP中
the idea of this is we're going to evaluate the pieces of the
我们想要去一条一条的求值
expressions that are in UNEV, one by one,
UNEV中的表达式
and move them from unevaluated in UNEV
然后把它们从UNEV中的待求值表
to evaluated in the arg list.
移动到ARGL中的已求值表中
OK. So we save argl.
然后我们保存ARGL
We assign to EXP the first operand
然后我们把UNEV中的第一个运算对象
of the stuff in UNEV.
赋值给EXP
Now, we check and see if that was the last operand.
然后我们检查它是否为最后一个运算对象
In this case, it is not.
在这里 它还不是
So we save the environment.
然后我们保存环境
We save UNEV
我们之所以保存UNEV
because those are all things we might need later.
是因为稍后我们可能会需要它们
We're going to need the environment
我们需要环境
to do some more evaluations.
来进行一些求值
We're going to need UNEV
我们需要UNEV寄存器来指示
to look at what the rest of those arguments were.
其余的待求值参数
We're going to assign continue
我们要把CONTINUE寄存器赋值为
a place called accumulate-args, or accumulate-arg.
ACCUMULATE-ARG这个标号
OK, now, we've set up for another call to eval-dispatch,
现在 我们已经准备好再次调用EVAL-DISPATCH了
All right, now, let me short-circuit this
现在让我把这个短路掉
so we don't go through the details of eval-dispatch.
这里我们不跟进EVAL-DISPATCH的细节
Eval-dispatch's contract says
EVAL-DISPATCH的约定说：
i'm going to end up,
我的调用完成后
the world will end up,
整个机器的状态会变为
with the value of evaluating this expression
也就是在ENV环境中求值EXP表达式
in this environment in the VAL register,
求值结果会保存在VAL寄存器中
and I'll end up there.
结束状态就是这样
So we short-circuit all of this,
那么我们把这些全都省略掉
and a 3 ends up in VAL.
最后VAL的内容是3
And, when we return from eval-dispatch,
并且当我们从EVAL-DISPATCH返回的时候
we're going to return to accumulate-arg.
我们会返回到ACCUMULAT-ARG这里
PROFESSOR: Accumulate-arg.
Sussman教授：跳转到ACCUMULATE-ARG
PROFESSOR: With 3 in the VAL register, OK?
Abelson教授：VAL寄存器里是3 对吧？
So that short-circuited that evaluation.
我们跳过了求值的细节
Now, what do we do?
现在我们要做什么？
We're going to go back and look at the rest of the arguments,
我们返回继续看剩下的参数
so we restore UNEV.
我们恢复UNEV
We restore ENV.
恢复ENV
We restore argl.
然后恢复ARGL
One thing.
这件事
PROFESSOR: Oops! Parity error.
Sussman教授：糟糕 奇偶错误
PROFESSOR: Restore argl.
Abelson教授：恢复ARGL
OK, we assign to argl consing on
然后 我们把VAL寄存器和ARGL给CONS起来
fetch of the value register to what's in argl.
然后赋值给ARGL寄存器
OK, we assign to UNEV the rest of the operands
我们把UNEV中剩余的运算对象
in fetch of UNEV,
赋值给UNEV
and we go back to eval-arg-loop.
然后我们返回到EVAL-ARG-LOOP
PROFESSOR: Eval-arg-loop.
Sussman教授：EVAL-ARG-LOOP
PROFESSOR: OK.
Abelson教授：好
Now, we're about to do the next argument,
现在我们处理下一个参数
so the first thing we do is save argl.
所以首先我们要保存ARGL
OK, we assign to EXP the first operand
然后我们把UNEV中的第一个运算对象
of fetch of UNEV.
赋给EXP
OK, we test and see if that's the last operand.
然后我们检查它是否为最后一个运算对象
In this case, it is
这里它是最后一个
so we're going to go to a special place
所以我们跳到一个特殊的地方
that says evaluate the last argument
来求值最后一个参数
because, notice,after evaluating the argument,
因为请注意 在求值这个参数之后
we don't need the environment any more.
我们就不再需要这个环境了
That's going to be the difference.
这就是区别
So here, at eval-last-arg,
在这里 在EVAL-LAST-ARG这里
which is assigned to continue accumulate-last-arg,
CONTINUE被赋值为了ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG
now, we're set up again for eval-dispatch.
现在我们再次为EVAL-DISPATCH做准备
We've got a place to go to when we're done.
我们有一个完成时要跳转的目的地
We've got an expression.
我们有一条表达式
We've got an environment.
还有一个环境
OK, so we'll short-circuit the call to eval-dispatch.
好 那么我们略过对EVAL-DISPATCH的调用
And what'll happen is there's a y there,
现在情况是这里有一个Y
it's 4 in that environment,
在这个环境中 它的值是4
so VAL will end up with 4 in it.
所以最终VAL寄存器将会是4
And, then, we're going to end up at accumulate-last-arg, OK?
然后我们就要以ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG结束了
So, at accumulate-last-arg,
因此 在ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG中
we restore argl.
我们恢复ARGL寄存器
We assign to argl, we assign to argl cons,
我们把ARGL赋值为
of fetch of the new value onto it,
将一个新值CONS在它上面的结果
so we cons a 4 onto that.
所以我们在它的旧值前CONS一个4
We restore what was saved in the function register.
我们恢复FUN寄存器中的内容
And notice, in this case,
需要注意的是 在则个例子中
it had not been destroyed,
FUN寄存器还没有被修改过
but in general, it will be.
但是通常来说 它会的
And now, we're ready to go off to apply-dispatch,
现在 我们将要调用APPLY-DISPATCH
Alright? So we've just gone through the eval.
所以我们刚刚步步跟进了EVAL过程
We evaluated the argument,
我们求值了运算符
the operator, and the arguments,
以及实际参数
and now, we're about to apply them.
现在我们要应用它们了
So we come off to apply-dispatch here
因此 我们来到APPLY-DISPATCH这里
We come off to apply-dispatch,
这是APPLY-DISPATCH的代码
and we're going to check whether it's a primitive
我们要检查它是一个基本过程
or a compound procedure.
还是一个复合过程
PROFESSOR: Yes.
Sussman教授：基本过程
PROFESSOR: All right.
Abelson教授：好的
So, in this case, it's a primitive procedure,
这里 它是一个基本过程
and we go off to primitive-apply.
因此 我们跳转到PRIMITIVE-APPLY
So we go off to primitive-apply,
我们来到PRIMITIVE-APPLY
that says assign to VAL
它说：把VAL赋值为
result of applying primitive procedure
把基本过程
of the function to the argument list.
应用在参数表的结果
PROFESSOR: I don't know how to add.
Sussman教授：我不知道怎么做加法
I'm just an execution unit.
我只是一个执行单元
PROFESSOR: Well, I don't know how to add either.
Abelson教授：我也不知道
I'm just the evaluator,
我只是一个求值器
so we need a primitive operator.
因此 我们需要一个基本运算执行器
Let's see, so the primitive operator,
那么 请问基本运算执行器
What's the... what's the sum of 3 and 4?
3+4等于多少？
AUDIENCE: 7.
学生：7
PROFESSOR: OK, 7.
Abelson教授：好 是7
PROFESSOR: Thank you.
Sussman教授：谢谢
PROFESSOR: Now, we restore continue,
Abelson教授：现在 我们恢复CONTINUE
and we go to fetch of continue.
执行(GOTO (FETCH CONTINUE))
PROFESSOR: Done.
Sussman教授：'DONE
PROFESSOR: OK.
Abelson教授：好
Well, that was in as much detail as you will ever see.
这些是你能看到的最细致的过程了
We'll never do it in as much detail again.
我们再也不会讲得这么细了
One very important thing to notice
有一件重要的事需要注意
is that we just executed a recursive procedure,
我们刚刚执行了一个递归过程
Right? This whole thing, we used a stack
我们在整个过程中使用了栈
and the evaluator was recursive.
而且求值器是递归的
A lot of people think the reason that you need a stack
有很多人以为在求值器中
and recursion in an evaluator
会用到栈和递归
is because you might be
或许是因为
evaluating recursive procedures like factorial or Fibonacci.
回去求值像阶乘或者FIB那样的递归过程
It's not true.
这并不正确
So you notice we did recursion here,
注意 我们在这里进行了递归
and all we evaluated was (+ x y)
而仅仅是去求值(+ X Y)
Right? The reason that you need recursion in the evaluator
在求值器中需要递归 实际上是因为
is because the evaluation process,
是因为求值过程本身
itself, is recursive.
就是递归的
Right? It's not because the procedure
并不是因为你在Lisp中
that you might be evaluating in LISP
要求值的那个过程
is a recursive procedure.
是一个递归过程
So that's an important thing
这一点很重要
that people get confused about a lot.
人们经常在这里被弄糊涂
The other thing to notice is that,
另一点要注意的是
when we're done here,
我们在这里完成之后
we're really done.
真正完成以后
Not only are we at done,
不仅仅是指我们在'DONE这个标号
but there's no accumulated stuff on the stack,
栈上也没有累积的东西了
Right? The machine is back to its initial state.
对吧？机器又回到了它的初始状态
So that's part of what it means to be done.
那就是“完成”的其中一部分意义
Another way to say that is
换句话说就是
the evaluation process has reduced
整个求值过程是把
the expression, plus X, Y,
(+ X Y)这条表达式
to the value here, 7.
归约为这里的7
And by reduced, I mean a very particular thing.
我所指的“归约”有特殊的意义
It means that there's nothing left on the stack.
也就是栈上没剩下任何东西了
The machine is now in the same state,
机器现在与初始状态相同
except there's something in the value register.
只是VAL寄存器里有一些东西
It's not part of a sub-problem of anything.
它不是任何问题的子问题
There's nothing to go back to.
不需要返回到其它地方
OK. Let's break.
好 这节课就讲到这里
Question?
有问题吗
AUDIENCE: The question here, in the stack,
学生：关于栈有一个问题
is because the data may be recursive.
由于数据有可能是递归的
You may have embedded expressions, for instance.
例如 嵌套的表达式
PROFESSOR: Yes, because you might have embedded expressions.
教授：是的 因为你可能遇到嵌套的表达式
But, again, don't confuse that
但是再说一遍 不要搞混
with what people sometimes mean by the data may be recursive,
有时候人们说数据是递归的
which is to say you have these list-structured,
他们说的是对于这些表结构的
recursive data list operations.
一些递归运算
That has nothing to do with it.
那和这没有关系
It's simply that the expressions contain sub-expressions.
这只是包含子表达式的表达式而已
AUDIENCE: Why is it that the order of the arguments in the arg list got reversed?
学生：为什么ARGL中参数的顺序是反过来的
PROFESSOR: Ah! Yes, I should've mentioned that.
教授：对 我应该提一嘴这个
Here, the reason the order is reversed--
之所以在这里把顺序反过来
it's a question of what you mean by reversed.
你首先定义怎么算“逆序”
I believe it was Newton.
我记得应该是牛顿
In the very early part of optics,
在光学发展的很早期
people realized
人们意识到
that when you look through the lens of your eye,
当你用眼睛通过透镜看东西的时候
the image was up-side down.
图像是上下颠倒的
And there was a lot of argument about
当时有很多的争论说
why that didn't mean you saw things up-side down.
为什么不能是你眼睛平时看见的都是上下颠倒的
So it's sort of the same issue.
这实际上是一样的道理
Reversed from what?
和什么相比反过来了
So we just need some convention.
我们只是需要一个约定
So all we.. The reason that they're coming at 4, 3
它们作为(4 3)出现的原因是
is because taking UNEV
是因为我们从UNEV中取出东西
and consing the result onto argl.
并且把它CONS到了ARGL上面
So you have to realize you've made that convention.
那么你要意识到你已经做了这个约定
The place that you have to realize that--
你需要意识到这点的地方有
well, there's actually two places.
实际上有两个地方
One is in apply-primitive-operator,
首先是在APPLY-PRIMITIVE-OPERATOR
which has to realize that
你要意识到
the arguments to primitives go in,
参数传入基本运算的顺序
the opposite order from the way you're writing them down.
是和你的书写顺序相反的
And the other one is, we'll see later
我们之后会在另外一处看到
when you actually go to bind a function's parameters,
当你实际绑定绑定函数的形式参数时
you should realize the arguments are going to come in
你要意识到参数进入的顺序
from the opposite order of the variables to which you're binding them.
和你要绑定这些变量时的顺序相反
So, if you just keep track of that,
所以如果你注意这些
there's no problem.
就没有问题了
Also, this is completely arbitrary
同样 这完全是随意的
because, if we'd done,
因为如果我们做了一个
say, an iteration through a vector assigning them,
比如 给向量的各个维度赋值的迭代
they might come out in the other order.
它们可能会以其它顺序输出
OK. So it's just a convention of the way
那么这只是这个求值器
this particular evaluator works.
工作时的一个约定
All right, let's take a break.
好 我们休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Sussman Jay Sussman
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
显式控制求值器
Professor: We just saw evaluating an expression
教授：我们已经学习了表达式的求值
and, of course, that was very simple one. But
虽然这只是一个非常简单的例子
in essence, it would be no different
但从本质上来说
if it was some big nested expression,
它跟那些大型嵌套表达式没什么不同
so there would just be deeper recursion on the stack.
后者只是在栈上递归得更深而已
But what I want to do now
我现在要为你们
is show you the last piece.
讲解最后一部分
I want to walk you around this eval and apply loop,
我要带着你们观察EVAL-APPLY循环
That's the thing we haven't seen, really.
我们还没有仔细研究过它
We haven't seen any compound procedures
我们还没有见过一个复合程序
where evalutation of procedure reduces to
对它的求值会归约为
where applying of procedure reduces to
对一个过程的应用
evaluating the body of the procedure,
进而是对过程体的求值
so let's just suppose we had this.
因此 假设我们有这个
Suppose we were looking at the procedure
假设我们正在考察
define F of A and B to be the sum of A and B.
(DEFINE (F A B) (+ A B)
So, as we typed in that procedure previously,
假设我们预先定义好了这个过程
and now we're going to evaluate F of X and Y
现在 我们将要求值(F X Y)
again, in this environment, E,0,
基于的环境是E0
where X is bound to 3 and Y is bound to 4.
其中X=3 Y=4
When the defined is executed,
当执行DEFINE的时候
remember, there's a lambda here,
还记得么 这里是一个LAMBDA
and lambdas create procedures.
LAMBDA会创建一个过程
And, basically, what will happen is,
基本上 会发生的事情是
in E0,
在环境E0中
we'll end up with a binding for F,
我们会得到F的绑定
which will say F is a procedure,
它指出F是一个过程
and its args are A and B,
这个过程的参数是A和B
and its body is plus a,b.
而过程体是(+ A B)
So that's what the environment would have looked like
这就是环境大概的样子
had we made that definition.
我们之前就定义过了
Then, when we go to evaluate F of X and Y,
然后 我们去求值(F X Y)
we'll go through exactly the same process
我们会仔细地解释每一步
that we did before.
就像之前那样
It's even the same expression.
不会跳过重复的表达式
The only difference is that
唯一的不同是
F, instead of having primitive "plus" in it
它的内部不再是基本的“+”过程
will have this thing.
它还有这个东西
And so we'll go through exactly the same process,
因此我们要进行相同的过程
except this time, when we end up
只不过这次
at apply-dispatch,
当我们停在APPLY-DISPATCH时
the function register, instead of having primitive plus,
FUN寄存器中不再是基本的“+”过程
will have a thing that will represent it saying procedure,
而是一个代表过程的东西
where the args are A and B,
其中参数为A和B
and the body is plus A, B.
过程体是(+ A B)
And, again, what I mean, by its ENV,
再强调一下 我所谓的ENV
I mean there's a pointer to it,
是一个指向环境的指针
so don't worry that I'm writing a lot of stuff there.
所以不用担心我在这里写了很多东西
There's a pointer to this procedure data structure.
这是一个指向代表过程的数据结构的指针
OK, so, we're in exactly the same situation.
因此 我们现在面临着相同的情况
We get to apply-dispatch,
我们来到了APPLY-DISPATCH
so, here, we come to apply-dispatch.
这是APPLY-DISPATCH的代码
Last time, we branched off to a primitive procedure.
上一次 我们分支跳转到了一个基本过程
Here, it says oh,
然而这一次
we now have a compound procedure,
我们遇到的是一个复合过程
so we're going to go off to compound-apply.
因此我们要跳转到COMPOUND-APPLY
Now, what's compound-apply?
COMPOUND-APPLY又是怎样定义的呢？
Well, remember what the meta-circular evaluator did?
还记得元循环求值器是怎么做的么？
Compound-apply said we're going to evaluate
COMPOUND-APPLY的执行步骤则是
the body of the procedure
在一个新的环境中
in some new environment.
求值一个过程的体
Where does that new environment come from?
这个新的环境来自于哪里呢？
We take the environment that was packaged with the procedure,
我们把跟过程一同打包的环境
we bind the parameters of the procedure
我们把过程的形式参数
to the arguments that we're passing in,
同传递进来的实际参数给绑定起来
and use that as a new frame to extend
把这个作为新的框架
the procedure environment.
来扩展过程附带的环境
And that's the environment
我们就是在这个环境中
in which we evaluate the procedure body,
求值过程的体
Right? That's going around the apply/eval loop.
对吧？这就是APPLY-EVAL循环做的事
That's apply coming back to call eval,
这就是APPLY回过头来调用EVAL
So, now, that's all we have to do in compound-apply.
因此 这就是我们要在COMPOUND-APPLY中要做的所有事
What are we going to do?
要怎么来实现呢？
We're going to manufacture a new environment.
我们要构造一个新的环境
And we're going to manufacture a new environment that,
而我们构造的这个新环境呢
let's see, that we'll call E1.
我们把它记作E1
E1 is going to be some environment where the
E1这个环境呢
where the parameters of the procedure,
存储了过程的参数绑定
Nwhere A is bound to 3, and B is bound to 4,
其中A=3 B=4
and it's linked to E0
并且它跟E0相连
because that's where f is defined.
这是因为 F就是在E0中定义的
And, in this environment,
因此 在这个环境中
we're going to evaluate the body of the procedure.
我们要来求值过程的体
So let's look at that, we're going
让我们来看一看
Here we are at compound-apply,
我们来看COMPOUND-APPLY的代码
which says assign to the expression register
首先是给EXP寄存器赋值
the body of the procedure
所赋的值是FUN寄存器
that's in the function register.
所指向过程的体
So I assign to the expression register
这样 我就将过程的体
the procedure body,
赋值给了EXP寄存器
OK?
对吧？
That's going to be evaluated in an environment
而这将在某个环境中求值
which is formed by making some bindings
这个环境是通过将FUN寄存器
using information determined by the procedure--
所指向的过程中的形式参数
that's what's in FUN-- and the argument list.
与实际参数绑定起来 得到的
And let's not worry about exactly what that does,
我们先不要关系它的具体细节
but you can see the information's there.
你可以知道它的最后结果
So make bindings will say oh,
因此MAKE-BINDINGS会说
the procedure, itself, had an environment attached to it.
过程本身就附带有一个环境
I didn't write that quite here.
在这里 我没有写出来
I should've said in environment
但我应该说过它有一个环境
because every procedure gets built
因为每个过程在构造时
with an environment.
都有一个环境
So, from that environment,
因此 通过这个环境
it knows
它能够知道
what the procedure's definition environment is.
定义该过程时的环境是怎样的
It knows what the arguments are.
它知道实际参数是什么
It looks at argl,
它查看ARGL
and then you see a reversal convention here.
然后你会在这里看到逆序的约定
It just has to know that argl is reversed,
它需要知道ARGL是逆序的
and it builds this frame, E,1.
然后它构造了这个框架 E1
All right, so, let's assume that
因此我们假设
that's what make bindings returns,
MAKE-BINDINGS返回的就是这些东西
so it assigns to ENV this thing, E,1.
然后 它把E1赋值给ENV
The next thing it says
下一步就是
is restore continue.
恢复CONTINUE
Remember what continue was here?
还记得CONTINUE之前是什么吗？
It got put up in the last segment.
在最后一段中
Continue got stored.
CONTINUE被保存了
That was the original done,
它的值是最初的'DONE
which said what are you going to do
这代表了
after you're done with this particular application?
在完成这项特定应用后要做的事
It was one of the very first things that happened
这是在求值整个应用时
when we evaluated the application.
最先发生的事儿
And now, finally, we're going to restore continue.
现在 我们要恢复CONTINUE了
Remember apply-dispatch's contract.
还记得APPLY-DISPATCH的约定么？
It assumes that where it should go to next
它假设下一步的跳转目标
was on the stack,
已经存放在栈上了
and there it was on the stack.
并且 这里确实存放在栈上了
Continue has done,
CONTINUE被赋值成了DONE
and now we're going to go back to eval-dispatch.
现在我们要回到EVAL-DISPATCH了
We're set up again.
我们要再次进行寄存器设置
We have an expression, an environment, and a place to go to.
我们有表达式、环境、下一步
We're not going to go through that
我不会再细讲了
because it's sort of the same expression.
因为它基本上就是相同的表达式
OK, but the thing, again, to notice
但是需要注意的是
is, at this point,
在这个时候
we have reduced the original expression, F,X,Y,
我们已经归约了原始表达式(F X Y)
We've reduced evaluating F,X,Y in environment E,0
通过在E0中求值(F X Y)
to evaluate plus A, B in E,1.
将其归约为在E1中求值(+ A B)
And notice, nothing's on the stack, right?
要注意 栈上并没有什么东西 对吧？
It's a reduction.
这是一个归约
At this point, the machine does not contain,
这个时候 机器的状态中
as part of its state,
并没有包含
the fact that it's in the middle of evaluating
它是求值过程F的
some procedure called f,
中间状态的事实
that's gone,
它消失了
Right? There's no accumulated state?
这里面没有积累的状态
Again, that's a very important idea.
注意 这个思想非常重要
That's the meaning of,
这意味着
when we used to write in the substitution model,
当我们使用代换模型时
this expression reduces to that expression.
一条表达式会归约到另一条表达式
And you don't have to remember anything.
而你不需要记住任何东西
And here, you see the meaning of reduction.
这里 你就见到了归约的真谛
At this point, there is nothing on the stack.
这个时候 栈上没有任何东西
See, that has very important consequences.
这样就有一个非常重要的结果
Let's go back and look at iterative factorial,
让我们回过头来看看迭代式阶乘
all right? Remember, this was some sort of loop
还记得吗？这是某种循环
and doing iter.
用来进行迭代
And we kept saying that's an iterative procedure,
我们不断强调 它是一个迭代过程
And what we wrote, remember,
还记得吗
are things like, we said,
我们使用它的时候
fact-iter of 5.
是像(FACT-ITER 5)这样调用它的
We wrote things like reduces to iter of 1, and 1, and 5,
然后我们把它归约成(ITER 1 1 5)
which reduces to iter of 1, and 2, and 5,
然后它归约成(ITER 1 2 5)
and so on, and so on, and so on.
等等等等
And we kept saying well, look,
然后我们又说 看
you don't have to build up any storage to do that.
为了实现这个效果 不需要存储任何东西
And we waved our hands,
我们摆了摆手 说
and said in principle, there's no storage needed.
“原则上 这不需要任何存储”
Now, you see no storage needed.
现在你们发现 确实不需要
Each of these is a real reduction, right?
这里的每一步都是真正的归约 对吧？
As you walk through these expressions,
随着你求值这些表达式
在求值这些表达式的过程中
what you'll see
你会发现
are these expressions on the stack
栈上的这些表达式
in some particular environment,
都在一个特定的环境中
and then these expressions, sorry, in the EXP register
抱歉 是EXP寄存器中的表达式
in some particular environment.
是在某个特定的环境中
And, at each point,
并且 在每一步
there'll be no accumulated stuff on the stack
栈上不会积累任何东西
because each one's a real reduction.
因为每一步都是真正的归约
All right, so, for example,
因此 举例来说
just to go through it in a little bit more care,
说得更仔细一点
if I start out with an expression that says something like,
如果我从这样的一条表达式开始
oh, say, fact-iter of 5 in some environment
比如说 在某个环境中计算(FACT-ITER 5)
that will, at some point, create an environment
它将在某个时刻创建一个环境
in which n is down to 5.
其中N=5
Let's call that--
我们把它写下来
And, at some point,
然后 在某个时候
the machine will reduce this whole thing
机器会归约这整个东西
to a thing that says that's really
将它归约为
iter of 1, and 1, and n,
(ITER 1 1 N)
evaluated in this environment, E,1
然后在环境E1中求值这条表达式
with nothing on the stack.
而不在栈上存放任何东西
See, at this moment, the machine is not remembering
看到了么 这时机器并不会记住
that evaluating this expression, iter--
求值这条ITER表达式--
which is the loop--
也就是某种循环--
is part of this thing called iterative factorial.
并不是FACT-ITER的一部分
It's not remembering that.
它不会记住这个事实
It's just reducing the expression to that, right?
它只是归约了该表达式
If we look again at the body of iterative factorial,
如果我们再来看迭代式阶乘的体
this expression has reduced to that expression.
这条表达式归约为了这条表达式
Oh, I shouldn't have the n there.
哦 这里漏了一个N
It's a slightly different convention
幻灯片中的约定
from the slide to the program.
和实际程序中稍有不同
And, then, what's the body of iter?
那么 ITER的体又是什么？
Well, iter's going to be an if,
ITER的体首先是一个IF--
and I won't go through the details of if.
我不会再深入IF语句的细节了
It'll evaluate the predicate.
它会对谓词求值
In this case, it'll be false.
本例中 会返回FALSE
And this iter will now reduce to the expression
然后这里的ITER会归约为表达式--
iter of whatever it says, star, counter product, and--
(ITER (* COUNTER PRODUCT)
what does it say--
按照它代码写的--
plus counter 1
(+ COUNTER 1))
in some other environment, by this time, E,2,
在另外的一个环境E2中求值
where E,2 will be set up having bindings
其中 E2会记录着
for product and counter.
PRODUCT和COUNTER的值
And it'll reduce to that.
它会被归约为这条语句
Right? It won't be remembering
它不会记得
that it's part of something that it has to return to.
它是一个需要返回到某处的一部分
And when iter calls iter again,
当ITER再次调用ITER时
it'll reduce to another thing that looks like this
它会归约为另一个像这样的东西
in some environment, E,3,
只是会在新环境E3中
which has new bindings for product and counter.
里面有关于PRODUCT和COUNTER新的绑定
OK? So, if you're wondering,
因此 如果你想知道
if you've always been queasy about
如果你一直感到不安
about how it is we've been saying those procedures
不知道为什么我们说这些过程
that look syntactically recursive,
虽然从语法上看起来是递归的
are, in fact, iterative,
但实际上是迭代的
run in constant space,
可以在常量空间中运行
well, I don't know if this makes you less queasy,
我不知道这么说是否打消了你们的疑虑
but at least it shows you what's happening.
但至少让你们知道发生了什么
There really isn't any buildup there.
这其中没有任何构造
Now, you might ask well, is there buildup
但你也会说 这里面还是有一些构造
in principle in these environment frames?
从原则上来说 我们也构造了环境框架
And the answer is yeah,
答案则是
you have to make these new environment frames,
你确实需要构建这些环境框架
but you don't have to hang onto them
但是 等你求值完毕后
when you're done.
不必保留它们
They can be garbage collected,
它们可以被废料收集
or the space can be reused automatically.
这些空间也可以被自动地重用
But you see the control structure of the evaluator
但你们可以看到求值器控制流
is really using this idea that you actually have a reduction,
的中心思想就是进行归约
so these procedures really are iterative procedures.
因此这些过程实际上是迭代过程
All right, let's stop for questions.
好吧 有什么问题么？
All right, let's break.
好吧 课件休息吧
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Sussman Jay Sussman
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
显示控制求值器
PROFESSOR: Let me contrast the iterative procedure
教授：跟迭代过程形成对比的是
just so you'll see where space does build up
确实会占用空间的
with a recursive procedure,
递归过程
so you can see the difference.
你们可以看到其中的区别
Let's look at the evaluation of recursive factorial.
让我们来看看递归式阶乘的求值
So, here's fact-recursive,
这里的FACT-REC
or standard factorial definition.
就是阶乘的标准定义
We said this one is still a recursive procedure,
这个当然是一个递归过程
but this is actually a recursive process.
它的计算过程也是递归的
And then, just to link it back to the way we started,
然后 只要把它和我们开始的方式联系起来
we said oh, you can see that it's going to be recursive process
我们会通过代换模型发现
by the substitution model
这是一个递归过程
because, if I say recursive factorial of 5,
因为 如果我调用(REC-FACT 5)
that turns into 5 times--
会变成(* 5
what is it, fact-rec, or record fact--
哦 这里是FACT-REC
5 times recursive factorial of 4,
(* 5 (FACT-REC 4))
which turns into 5 times 4 times fact-rec of 3,
又会变成(* 5 (* 4 (FACT-REC 3)))
which returns into 5 times 4 times 3 times
又会变成(* 5 (* 4 (* 3 (* ...
and so on, right?
以此类推
The idea is there was this chain of stuff building up,
关键点就是 有一条链条被不断构造出来
which justified, in the substitution model,
这就在代换模型中证明了
the fact that it's recursive.
FACT-REC是递归的
And now, let's actually see that chain of stuff build up
现在 让我们来看看这条构造起来的链条
and where it is in the machine, OK?
它又是在机器中的什么地方？
All right, well, let's imagine we're going to start out again.
好吧 让我们想象一下要从哪里开始
We'll tell it to evaluate recursive factorial of 5
我们告诉机器 求值(FACT-REC 5)
in some environment, again, E0, where
基于的环境是E0
where recursive factorial is defined, OK?
也就是定义FACT-REC时的环境
Well, now we know what's eventually going to happen.
现在 我们知道最终要发生什么
This is going to come along,
首先
it'll evaluate those things,
它会对这些东西求值
figure out it's a procedure,
发现它是一个过程
build somewhere over here an environment, E1,
在这里创建一个新环境E1
which has n bound to 5,
其中N=5
which hangs off of E0,
并且与E0相连
which would be, presumably,
这个E0也就是
the definition environment of recursive factorial.
定义FACT-REC的那个环境
OK? And, in this environment,
然后 在E1这个环境中
it's going to go off and evaluate the body.
求值过程的体
So, again, the evaluation here will reduce to
因此 在这里求值会归约为
evaluating the body in E1.
在E1中求值过程的体
That's going to look at an if,
这就需要求值IF语句
and I won't go through the details of if.
而我不会讲解IF语句的细节
It'll look at the predicate.
IF语句会求值谓词
It'll decide it eventually has to evaluate the alternative.
最后发现需要求值ELSE子句
So this whole thing, again, will reduce to
因此 这里的整个部分 会归约为
the alternative of recursive factorial,
FACT-REC的ELSE子句
the alternative clause,
也就是谓词为假的部分
which says that this whole thing reduces to times n
整个表达式就归约为了(* N
of recursive factorial of n minus 1
(FACT-REC (- N 1))
in the environment E1
求值的环境是E1
OK? So the original expression, now, is going to reduce
因此 最初的表达式现在就会归约为
to evaluating that expression, all right?
求值这样的一个表达式
OK? Now we have an application.
而现在 我们面对的是一个应用
We did an application before.
我们之前求值过应用
Remember what happens in an application?
还记得要怎么求值应用么？
The first thing you do is you go off and you
正式求值一个应用之前
you save the value of the continue register on the stack.
你需要把CONTINUE寄存器的值保存在栈上
So the stack here is going to have done in it.
此时 栈上会有一个值'DONE
And then you're going to set up to evaluate the sub-parts.
接下来 你要为求值子部分做准备
OK? So here we go off to evaluate the sub-parts.
因此 我们在这里开始求值子部分
First thing we're going to do is evaluate the operator.
首先要做的是求值运算符
What happens when we evaluate an operator?
运算符是怎样求值的呢？
Well, we arrange things so that
我们通过一些手段
the operator ends up in the expression register.
将EXP寄存器指向运算符对应的过程
The environments in the ENV register
并且让ENV寄存器指向求值的环境
continue someplace
而把CONTINUE寄存器赋值为
where we're going to go evaluate the arguments.
用于求值参数的EVAL-ARGS
And, on the stack,
并且 我们把
we've saved the original continue,
CONTINUE的原始值保存在栈上
which is where we wanted to be when we're all done.
我们完成所有工作后 就会跳转到这个地方
And then the things we needed
在我们求值完运算符后
when we're going to get done evaluating the operator,
需要做的则是
the things we'll need to evaluate the arguments,
求值对实际参数进行求值
namely the environment and those arguments,
也就是这个环境和这些参数
those unevaluated arguments,
这些尚未求值的实际参数
so there they are sitting on the stack.
它们现在都还在栈上
And we're about to go off to evaluate the operator.
我们现在就要先来求值运算符
Well, when we return from this particular call--
当我们从这个调用返回时
so we're about to call eval-dispatch here--
在这里 我们将要去调用EVAL-DISPATCH
when we return from this call,
当我们从这个调用返回时
the value of that operator,
这个运算符所对应的值
which, in this case,
在本例中
is going to be the primitive multiplier procedure,
也就是基本的乘法过程
will end up in the FUN register.
会存放在FUN寄存器中
We're going to evaluate some arguments.
我们要去求值实际参数
They will evaluate n here.
现在这里求值N
That'll give us 5, in this case.
本例中 会返回5
We're going to put that in the argl register,
然后我们会把它放入ARGL寄存器
and then we'll go off to evaluate the second operand.
然后我们会去求值第二个运算对象
So, at the point where we go off to evaluate the second operand--
就在我们准备求值第二个运算对象之时
and I'll skip details like computing,
我会省略计算
N minus 1, and all of that--
(- N 1)之类的细节
but, when we go off to evaluate the second operand,
但是 当我们去求值第二个运算对象时
that will eventually reduce to another call to fact-recursive.
会最终归约为对FACT-REC的另一个调用
And, what we've got on the stack here is
现在 我们在栈上有
the operator from that combination that we're going to use it in
来自于这个组合式的运算符
and the other argument.
以及其它的参数
OK? So, now, we're set up for another call
现在 我们已经准备好
to recursive factorial.
去调用另外的FACT-REC了
And, when we're done with this one,
而让我们完成了这个调用以后
we're going to go to accumulate the last arg.
我们就要跳转到ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG
and remember what that'll do?
还记得这是做什么的么？
That'll say oh,
它会说
whatever the result of this has to get combined with that,
我们会把这个调用的结果
and we're going to multiply them.
和这个5相乘
But, notice now,
但是请注意
we're at another recursive factorial.
我们现在处于另一个递归阶乘中
We're about to call eval-dispatch again,
我们又要再次调用EVAL-DISPATCH
except we haven't really reduced it
然而我们并没有真正地“归约”它
because there's stuff on the stack now.
因为现在栈上还有东西
The stuff on the stack says oh, when you get back,
栈上的这些东西说：“当你返回时”
you'd better multiply it by the 5 you had hanging there.
你最好把结果和放在这里的5相乘
So, when we go off to make another call,
所以当我们进行另外的调用
we evaluate the n minus 1.
求值(- N 1)
That gives us another environment which
这会返回给我们另一个环境
in which the new n's going to be down to 4.
其中N的新值为4
And we're about to call eval-dispatch again.
然后又将调用EVAL-DISPATCH
We get another call.
我们又创建了另一个调用
That 4 is going to end up in the same situation.
这个4又会遇到相同的情况
We'll end up with another call to fact-recursive n.
我们最后会遇到对(FACT-REC N)的又一次调用
And sitting on the stack will be the stuff from the original one
而这时候 栈上会有从最初的调用
and, now, the subsidiary one we're doing.
到最近一次调用的东西
And both of them are waiting for the same thing.
它们都在等待同一个东西
They're going to go to accumulate a last argument.
它们都要跳转到ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG
And then, of course, when we go to the fourth call,
当然 当我们进行第四次调用时
the same thing happens.
会发生同样的事
And this goes on, and on, and on.
如此往复
And what you see here on the stack,
在这里 你在栈上看到的
exactly what's sitting here on the stack,
栈上面实际存放的是
the thing that says times and 5.
基本过程*以及5
And what you're going to do with that
而你要把它用来
accumulate that into a last argument.
调用ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG
That's exactly this, right?
就是这样 对吧？
This is exactly where that stuff is hanging.
这跟它们在表达式中的顺序是一致的
Effectively, the operator you're going to apply,
实际上 你将要应用的运算符
the other argument that it's got
以及当你返回时
to be multiplied by when you get back
需要去求积的参数
and sort of the parentheses,
以及这里的括号
which says yeah, what you wanted to do was accumulate them.
都在告诉你 在对它们进行积累
So, you see, the substitution model is not such a lie.
因此 你可以看到代换模型并不是这样的谎言
That really is, in some sense,
从某种意义上来说 它实际上是
what's sitting right on the stack.
存在于栈上的那些东西
All right, so that,
好吧 从某种意义上来说
in some sense, should explain for you,
应该给你们解释了
or at least convince you,
或者 至少让你们相信
that somehow, this evaluator is managing
求值器会通过某些方式
to take these procedures and execute some of them iteratively
迭代地去求值某些过程
and some of them recursively,
而递归地去求值另外的过程
even though, as syntactically,
尽管从语法上看
they look like recursive procedures.
它们都是递归过程
How's it managing to do that?
它又是如何做到的呢？
Well, the basic reason it's managing to do that
其中的基本原因就是
is the evaluator is set up
求值器被设置为
to save only what it needs later.
只保存那些稍后会用到的东西
So, for example, at the point where you've reduced
比如说 当你在把
evaluating an expression and an environment
在一个环境中求值表达式归约为
to applying a procedure to some arguments,
将某个过程应用在参数上时
it doesn't need that original environment anymore
它就不再需要最初的环境了
because any environment stuff will be packaged inside the procedures
因为所需要的环境信息都被打包到
where the application's going to happen.
需要应用的那个过程中了
All right, similarly,
同样 类似地
when you're going along evaluating an argument list,
当你求值一个参数表时
when you've finished evaluating the list,
当你完成对表的求值时
when you're finished evaluating the last argument,
当你求值完最后一个参数时
you don't need that argument list any more, right?
你就不再需要这个参数表了 对吧？
And you don't need the environment where
你也就不再需要
those arguments would be evaluated.
求值这些参数所需的环境了
So the basic reason that this interpreter is being so smart
所以这个解释器如此“智能”的根本原因
is that it's not being smart at all, it's being stupid.
根本不是因为它“智能” 只是因为它老实
It's just saying I'm only going to save what I really need.
它的原则就是：“只保存那些需要的”
Well, let me show you here.
这里 让我来给你们展示
Here's the actual thing that's making a tail recursive.
这是致使尾递归的根本原因
Remember, it's the restore of continue.
要记住 (RESOTRE CONTINUE)这条代码
It's saying when I go off to evaluate the procedure body,
它指的是 当我去求值过程体的时候
I should tell eval to come back to
我应该告诉EVAL返回到
the place where that original
最初的求值
evaluation was supposed to come back to.
应该返回的地方
So, in some sense,
因此 从某种角度来说
you want to say what's the actual line that makes tail recursive
你想知道是哪一行代码致使了尾递归
It's that one.
那么就是这一行
If I wanted to build a non-
出于某些奇怪的原因
tail recursive evaluator, for some strange reason,
如果我想构建一个没有尾递归的求值器
all I would need to do
我需要做的就是
is, instead of restoring continue at this point,
在这里先不要去恢复CONTINUE
I'd set up a label down here
而是在这里建立一个标号
called, "Where to come back after you've finished applying the procedure."
用来标识完成过程应用后的返回位置
Instead, I'd set continue to that.
而我会把CONTINUE设置为这个标号
I'd go to eval-dispatch,
然后跳转到EVAL-DISPATCH
and then eval-dispatch would come back here.
然后EVAL-DISPATCH会回到这里
At that point,
而这时
I would restore continue
我会恢复CONTINUE
and go to the original one.
并回到最初的返回位置
So here, the only consequence of that
因此 这里唯一的后果就是
would be to make it non-tail recursive.
解释器不再是尾递归的了
It would give you exactly the same answers,
它会给你完全相同的答案
except if you did that iterative factorial
只是当你执行迭代式阶乘
and all those iterative procedures,
或者其它迭代过程时
it would execute recursively.
它都会递归地去执行
Well, I lied to you a little bit, but just a little bit,
然而 我对你们撒了一个小谎
because I showed you a slightly
因为我演示的
over-simplified evaluator
一个有些过于简化的解释器
where it assumes that each procedure --
这个解释器假设每个过程
each procedure body has only one expression.
只含有一条表达式
Remember, in general,
还记得吗 通常来说
a procedure has a sequence of expressions in it.
过程的体是多条表达式组成的序列
So there's nothing really conceptually new.
所以没有什么新概念
Let me just show you the actual evaluator
让我来展示一下实际的求值器
that handles sequences of expressions.
是怎么来处理表达式序列的
This is compound-apply now,
这是现在的COMPOUND-APPLY
and the only difference from the old one
和之前的唯一不同是
is that, instead of going off to eval directly,
它不再直接地跳转到EVAL
it takes the whole body of the procedure,
它先获取整个过程的体
which, in this case, is a sequence of expressions,
在本例中 也就是表达式序列
and goes off to eval-sequence.
然后跳转到EVAL-SEQUENCE
And eval-sequence is a little loop
EVAL-SEQUENCE是一个小型的循环
that, basically, does these evaluations one at a time.
然后每次求值一条表达式
So it does an evaluation.
就是这样来求值的--
Says oh, when I come back,
当它求值完一条表达式后
I'd better come back here to do the next one.
会跳转到这里 去求值下一条
And, when I'm all done,
当我完成了所有的求值后
when I want to get the last expression,
我想要跳转到LAST-EXP
I just restore my continue
我就只需要恢复CONTINUE寄存器
and go off to eval-dispatch.
然后跳转到EVAL-DISPATCH
And, again, if you wanted for some reason
同样的 如果你想要在这种求值器中
to break tail recursion in this evaluator,
破坏尾递归机制
all you need to do is not handle the last expression, especially.
你只需要在LAST-EXP中不做特殊处理即可
Just say, after you've done the last expression,
也就是说 当你处理完最后一条表达式
come back to some other place
你跳转到另外一个地方
after which you restore continue.
在那个地方去恢复CONTINUE
And, for some reason,
出于某些原因
a lot of LISP evaluators tended to work that way.
很多Lisp求值器倾向于这么做
And the only consequence of that is that
这样做的后果就是
iterative procedures built up stack.
迭代式过程也会使栈增长
And it's not clear why that happened.
还不清楚为什么会这样
All right. Well, let me just sort of summarize,
好吧 我稍微来总结一下
since this is a lot of details
毕竟这是一个大程序
in a big program.
又有很多细节
But the main point is that
但关键点就是
it's no different,
从概念上来说
conceptually, from translating any other program.
这跟翻译其它程序没什么不同
And the main idea is that
核心思想就是
we have this universal evaluator program,
我们已经有了通用求值器程序
the meta-circular evaluator.
一个元循环求值器
If we translate that into LISP,
如果我们把它翻译为了Lisp
then we have all of LISP.
那么我们就有了Lisp的所有东西
And that's all we did.
我们就是这么来做的
The second point is that the magic's gone away.
第二点则是 魔法消失了
There should be no more magic in this whole system, right?
这整个系统不再神秘了 对吧？
In principle, it should all be very clear
原则上来说 这应该相当清楚了
except, maybe, for how list structured memory works,
只是还不太了解表结构的内存管理
and we'll see that later.
我们后面会讲
But that's not very hard.
这也并不困难
The third point is that
第三点就是
all this tail recursion
所有的这些尾递归
came from the discipline of eval being very careful
来自于严格的求值纪律
to save only what it needs next time.
也就是只保存那些后面会用到的东西
It's not some arbitrary thing
而不是一些比较随意的原则
where we're saying well, whenever we call a sub-routine,
比如 无论什么时候我们调用一个子过程
we'll save all the registers in the world and come back?
我们会保存所有的寄存器并且返回
See, sometimes it pays to really worry about efficiency.
有些时候为了提效 这样做很值得
And, when you're down in the guts of your evaluator machine,
当你研究求值机器的内部原理时
it really pays to think about things like that
这类东西就很值得去研究
because it makes big consequences.
因为它会带来显著的不同
Well, I hope what this has done
我想现在基本上已经
is really made the evaluator seem concrete.
把这个求值器讲得很清楚了
I hope you really believe
我希望你们能相信
that somebody could hold a LISP
真的有人能够
LISP evaluator in the palm of their hand.
将一个Lisp求值器放在掌心之中
Maybe to help you believe that, here's a
为了让你们死心塌地
here's a LISP evaluator
我给你们看一个Lisp求值器
that I'm holding the palm of my hand.
它就在我的手掌中
And this is a chip which is actually
这块求值器芯片实际上
quite a bit more complicated than the evaluator I showed you.
比我给你们展示的求值器还要复杂
Uh.. maybe, here's a better picture of it.
这张图片效果更好
What there is,
在这上面
is you can see the same overall structure.
你可以看到相同的宏观结构
This is a register array.
这是寄存器阵列
These are the data paths.
这些是数据通路
Here's a finite state controller.
这里有是有穷状态控制器
And again, finite state,
再强调一下 是有穷状态
that's all there is.
全都在这里了
And somewhere there's external memory
在另外的地方还有外部存储
that'll worry about things.
用来存储数据
And this particular one is very complicated
而这块芯片非常复杂
because it's trying to run LISP fast.
是因为它尝试更快地运行Lisp
And it has some very, very fast parallel operations in there
它具有非常非常之快的并行运算
like, if you want to index into an array,
比如说 如果你想要索引一个数组
simultaneously check that the index is an integer,
同时又要检查该索引是否为一个整数
check that it doesn't exceed the array bands,
以及该索引没有越界
and go off and do the memory access,
同时还要进行内存存取
and do all those things simultaneously.
它会同时进行这些事
And then, later, if they're all OK,
如果这些操作都没有问题的话
actually get the value there.
最终就会在这里得到结果
So there are a lot of complicated operations
因此 数据通路中大量的
in these data paths for making LISP run in parallel.
复杂运算使得Lisp能够并行运行
It's a completely non-risk
这完全是求值Lisp的
philosophy of evaluating LISP.
一种无冒险的哲学
And then, this microcode is pretty complicated.
并且 这个的微指令也相当复杂
Let's see, there's what?
让我先看一看
There's about 389 instructions of
这其中有大概389条
of 220-bit microcode sitting here
220比特的微指令
because these are very complicated data paths.
只因为这些数据通路非常复杂
And the whole thing has about 89,000 transistors, OK?
整个芯片大概有89,000支晶体管
OK. Well, I hope that that takes away a lot of the mystery.
好吧 我希望通过这节课解答了大部分疑惑
Maybe somebody wants to look at this.
也许你们想看一看这块芯片
OK. Let's stop.
好吧 先讲到这里
Questions?
有问题吗？
AUDIENCE: OK, now, it sounds like what you're saying is that,
学生：您所讲的 听起来像是
with the restore continue put in the proper place,
如果把(RESTORE CONTINUE)放在合适的地方
that procedures that would invoke a recursive process
这样之前递归求值的过程
now invoke an iterative process
现在就会变成迭代求值的
just by the way that the eval-sequence source?
（意义不明）
PROFESSOR: I think the way I'd prefer to put it is that,
教授：我想我应该这么来说
with restore continue put in the wrong place,
如果把(RESTORE CONTINUE)放在了错误的位置
you can cause any syntactically-looking recursive procedure,
你就会让那些语法上看起来像递归的过程
in fact, to build up stack as it runs.
在运行的时候不断地扩张栈
But there's no reason for that,
但这样是没有原因的
so you might want to play around with it.
你可以自己去试一试
You can just switch around two or three instructions
你可以在COMPOND-APPLY返回后
in the way compound-apply comes back,
交换两、三条语句的顺序
and you'll get something which isn't tail recursive.
那么你得到的就不再是尾递归了
But the thing I wanted to emphasize
我只是想强调
is there's no magic. there's no
这其中没有什么魔法
It's not as if
这并不是
there's some very clever pre-processing program
有什么智能的预处理程序
that's looking at this procedure, factorial iter,
它会分析FACT-ITER这个程序
and say oh, gee, um
然后说
I really notice that
我注意到
I don't have to push stack in order to do this.
完成这个调用 不需要我进行压栈
Some people think that that's what's going on.
但是有些人是这么认为的
It's something much, much more dumb than that,
而是一种比这个还要蠢的机制
it's this one place you're putting the restore instruction.
就是在合适的地方插入RESTORE指令
It's just automatic.
就可以自动地实现
AUDIENCE: But that's not affecting the time complexity is it?
学生：但这不会影响到时间复杂度 对吧？
PROFESSOR: No.
教授：不会
AUDIENCE: It's just that it's handling it recursively
学生：它不会迭代地处理
instead of iteratively.
而是会递归地处理
But, in terms of the order of time it takes to finish the operation,
但就从完成这两个运算的时间来说
it's the same one way or the other, right?
它们都是相同的 对吧？
PROFESSOR: Yes.
教授 ：是的
Tail recursion is not going to change the time complexity of anything
尾递归不会改变任何东西的时间复杂度
because, in some sense,
因为 从某种意义上来说
it's the same algorithm that's going on.
两者都是相同的算法
What it's doing is really making this thing run as an iteration.
它只是让这个过程迭代地运行
Right? Not going to run out of memory
这样 当参数很大时
you know counting up to a giant number
它不会耗尽所有的内存
simply because the stack would get pushed.
因为这其中没有压栈
See, the thing you really have to believe is that,
事实上 你们需要相信
when we write--
当我们编写--
see, we've been writing all these things called iterations,
我们一直把这些代码称作“迭代”
infinite loops, define loop to be called loop.
把(DEFINE (LOOP) (LOOP))称作无穷循环
That's is as much an iteration
这就是一个迭代
you know as if we wrote do forever loop.
跟我们用DO语句来写无穷循环是一样的
It's just syntactic sugar as the difference.
它们只是语法上不同而已
These things are real, honest to god, iterations?
它们实际上都是迭代
They don't change the time complexity,
它们并不改变时间复杂度
but they turn them into real iterations.
但是它会把它们变成真正的迭代
All right, thank you.
好吧 下课
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP